{"tossups": [{"question": "One family from this city, the Embriaco, stylized themselves as the Lords of Gibelet, since they ruled the `\tcity of Byblos. The Bank of Saint George operated in this city. It's not Rome, but one leader of this city, who took the title of \"perpetual censor,\" reformed its constitution to create the alberghi. The decision to catapult bodies over one colony controlled by this city in Gazaria likely contributed to the Black Death; that city on the (*) Black Sea is Caffa. The Battle of Preveza saw the defeat of one admiral from this city, Andrea Doria. This city controlled the island of Corsica to its south. Like Venice, this city was led by a doge. For 10 points, name this Italian city on the Liguarian sea, the birthplace of Christopher Columbus.", "answer": "Republic of Genoa", "subcategory": "European History", "category": "History"}, {"question": "This building is referred to as an \"Enigma\" in the title of a Joan Breton Connelly book. Alan LeQuire created a gilded replica of a sculpture from this building. The columns of this building lean slightly inward, likely to give the building an appearance of strength, although its stylobate is curved. A frieze in this building shows twelve figures with their backs turned to children helping an adult fold a piece of cloth. (*) Ictinus and Callicrates designed this building. A replica of this building in Nashville contains a recreation of the chryselephantine statue of its dedicatee that was made by Phidias. The Elgin Marbles were taken from this building to the British Museum. For 10 points, name this large temple on the Acropolis dedicated to Athena.", "answer": "The Parthenon", "subcategory": "Other Fine Arts", "category": "Fine Arts"}, {"question": "A poem named for a village in this country notes that \"The houses are all gone under the sea / The dancers are all gone under the hill\" and ends with a description of \"The wave cry, the wind cry, the vast waters / Of the petrel and the porpoise.\" A community in this country titles a poem that describes \"Midwinter spring\" as \"sempiternal though sodden towards sundown\" and ends by declaring \"the fire and the rose are one.\" A poem titled for a house in this country notes that \"Time present and time past / Are both perhaps present in time future.\" Except for (*) The Dry Salvages, each of the Four Quartets are named for locations in this country. This country's legend of the Fisher King is referenced throughout The Waste Land. For 10 points, name this European country, the adopted home of T. S. Eliot.", "answer": "The United Kingdom of Great Britain and Northern Ireland [or Great Britain; accept England, accept Wales or Scotland after the Fisher King clue]", "subcategory": "Poetry", "category": "Literature"}, {"question": "The third part of this novel ends with a description of two tomcats who scrape the remains of dead birds off of engine grilles. After purchasing rope, two characters in this novel visit a convent in an attempt to buy black stockings from a nun. While in prison, a character in this novel writes a letter to Don Cullivan and traps a squirrel he nicknames \"Red.\" The guitar of one character in this novel is stolen while he drinks with Otto and the Cowboy in (*) Acapulco. A parole letter in this novel notes that one character's parents were the rodeo duo Tex John and Florence Buckskin; that character is pursued by Alvin Dewey. In this novel, Kenyon and Nancy are shot after being tied up by Perry Smith and Richard Hickock. For 10 points, name this \"nonfiction novel\" that describes the murder of the Clutter family in Holcomb, Kansas, by Truman Capote.", "answer": "In Cold Blood", "subcategory": "Long Fiction", "category": "Literature"}, {"question": "This quantity first increases and then decreases as per capita income rises in the Kuznets curve. Globalization and technological changes are not the cause of the rise of this quantity in the US, according to a Joseph Stiglitz book titled for the The Price of this quantity. This quantity increases when r is greater than g, according to the book (*) Capital in the Twenty-First Century by Thomas Piketty. One measure of this phenomenon is calculated by finding the ratio A over A plus B on a Lorenz curve. This phenomenon is measured by the Gini coefficient. Examples of this phenomenon include \"the top 20% control 80% of the wealth.\" For 10 points, name this phenomenon, in which wealth is unevenly distributed across a population.", "answer": "economic inequality [accept any form of inequality]", "subcategory": "Social Science", "category": "Social Science"}, {"question": "This geographic region's Isua greenstone belt contains one stromatolite contender for the oldest evidence of life on Earth. Records from Camp Century in this geographical region led to the discovery of Dansgaard- Oeschger events, short intense temperature increases. A proposed mining project at Kvanefjeld was the major issue in a recent election in this geographic region. The largest (*) national park in the world protects this landmass's northeast coast. On this landmass, a supply mission to Eismitte claimed the life of Alfred Wegener. This landmass's northernmost point is Cape Morris Jesup. The largest non-Antarctic ice sheet covers this landmass, whose largest city is Nuuk. For 10 points, name this Denmark-controlled largest island in the world, located in the Arctic Ocean.", "answer": "Greenland [accept Kalaallit Nunaat]", "subcategory": "Geography", "category": "Geography"}, {"question": "A work by this artist depicts a young woman playing the title instrument and staring off into the left side of the painting, which was this artist's first work to be accepted in the Paris Salon. In another painting by this painter, a woman wearing a white dress reclines in a patterned chair while reading the newspaper and is titled (*) Reading La Figaro. Degas remarked \"there is someone who feels as I do\" after viewing this artist's works, and he collaborated on this artist's work Little Girl in a Blue Armchair. One of this artist's works depicts a mother in a striped dress washing her daughter's feet. For 10 points, name this artist, one of the \"three great ladies of impressionism,\" who painted The Child's Bath.", "answer": "Mary Cassatt", "subcategory": "Visual Fine Arts", "category": "Fine Arts"}, {"question": "Along with iodine, this compound forms a coordination complex with rhodium in an industrial process developed by BASF. This compound is added to methanol to form acetic acid. This compound reacts with water to form carbon dioxide and hydrogen in the water-gas shift reaction, a side reaction that is suppressed by the Cativa process. This compound is found alongside hydrogen in (*) syngas. This compound is produced in incomplete, but not complete, combustion. Along with smoke, this colorless, odorless, lethal gas is sensed by many detectors. This compound has 230 times the binding affinity to hemoglobin compared to oxygen. For 10 points, name this compound that consists of one atom each of carbon and oxygen.", "answer": "carbon monoxide [or CO]", "subcategory": "Chemistry", "category": "Science"}, {"question": "Remnants of forces from this rebellion went south to fight in flag gangs in the Haw Wars. The leader of this rebellion gained his vision for establishing his regime after going to Thistle Mountain, where he first met many of his future commanders. The rebel side in this rebellion was weakened when their East King tried to stage a revolt in which the North King also died. (*) Charles Gordon was put in charge of the Ever Victorious Army that ended up putting down this rebellion. After this rebellion, the victors carried out reprisals against the Hakka population. The state established from this rebellion proclaimed itself the Heavenly Kingdom in the city of Nanjing. For 10 points, name this rebellion led by Hong Xiuquan, which created a state influenced by Christian theology and fought against the Qing dynasty in the 1850s and 1860s.", "answer": "Taiping Rebellion [accept Taiping Heavenly Kingdom]", "subcategory": "World History", "category": "History"}, {"question": "By a theorem of Euler, if n is a number named for these shapes, then the number of even partitions of n and odd partitions of n differ by 1. Since the number of sides of these shapes is the second Fermat prime, these shapes are constructible by the Gauss - Wantzel theorem. Numbers named for these shapes are of the form n times the quantity 3 n plus 1, over 2. 12 of these shapes and 20 hexagons form the faces of a (*) truncated icosahedron. The ratio between the length of a diagonal to the length of a side equals the golden ratio in these shapes. A pyramid with one of these shapes as its base has 6 vertices. The exterior angle of a regular one of these shapes is 72 degrees, and the sum of the interior angles of these shapes is 540 degrees. For 10 points, name these polygons with 5 sides.", "answer": "pentagon [accept regular pentagon or pentagonal numbers]", "subcategory": "Math", "category": "Science"}, {"question": "The function of this system is supported by SP-B and SP-C, which lower the Krafft temperature. It's not a buffer system, but pH levels in the fluid surrounding the medulla oblongata are used to control this system. A mixture of DPPC and other proteins are used to support one part of this system. This system is supported by the pleural membranes. Mary Ellen Avery showed that RDS, which affects this system, is caused by a lack of (*) surfactant. In humans, this system uses negative pressure to perform one of its main functions. COPD affects this system. The epiglottis prevents food from entering parts of this system. Parts of this system include the diaphragm and bronchioles. For 10 points, name this body system that includes the lungs and helps you breathe.", "answer": "respiratory system [or pulmonary system; accept ventilatory system; prompt on cardiopulmonary system; prompt on breathing; prompt on lung surfactant system; prompt on lungs]", "subcategory": "Biology", "category": "Science"}, {"question": "In the \"liberty scene\" of a work by this composer, the mezzo-soprano air \"Oh Liberty\" is followed by the duet \"Come, ever smiling liberty.\" \"Let God Arise\" is the last of eleven settings of psalms this composer wrote for his patron, the Chandos Anthems. The majority of one work by this composer is sung by roles simply known as the Israelitish Man and Woman. This composer of (*) Acis and Galatea included the chorus \"See, The Conqu'ring Hero Comes\" in another oratorio. One work by this composer has the strings imitate shepherd bagpipers in the instrumental section Pifa. A work by this composer with libretto by Charles Jennens includes the aria \"I Know That My Redeemer Liveth.\" For 10 points, name this composer of Judas Maccabeus and an oratorio that contains the \"Hallelujah\" chorus, Messiah. --------------------------------------------------------------------------------", "answer": "George Frideric Handel  --------------------------------------------------------------------------------", "subcategory": "Auditory Fine Arts", "category": "Fine Arts"}, {"question": "This person discussed a question and answer session they did with a seven year old girl as part of the speech \"To Restore America.\" This person quoted FDR to end one speech with the line, \"You and I have a rendezvous with destiny.\" In one campaign where he defeated former mayor George Christopher, this person promised to \"send the welfare bums back to work.\" This person said he would \"clean up the mess at Berkeley\" in a campaign where he defeated Pat Brown to become governor of (*) California. This person supported Barry Goldwater in the 1964 speech \"A Time for Choosing.\" During a speech at the Brandenburg gate, this person asked, \"Mr. Gorbachev, tear down this wall.\" For 10 points, name this person who defeated Jimmy Carter to become president in 1980.", "answer": "Ronald Reagan", "subcategory": "American History", "category": "History"}, {"question": "NetChoice and the CCIA sued to overturn a law passed in this state for violating Section 230; that law would have prevented social media companies from banning political candidates. This state passed Senate Bill 1028, an anti-trans sports ban, on the first day of pride month. The mayor of one city in this state, Charles Burkett, claimed that \"we are not resource poor.\" A 2018 letter from Morabito Consultants pointed out repairs needed for (*) Champlain Towers South, which is located in this state. This state's Agriculture Commissioner Nikki Fried and Rep. Charlie Crist are attempting to unseat a governor who defeated Andrew Gillum in 2018. This state's governor, Ron Desantis, said he was working on a \"dual track\" with Hurricane Elsa. For 10 points, name this state where a Surfside condo collapsed in Miami-Dade county.", "answer": "Florida", "subcategory": "Current Events", "category": "Current Events"}, {"question": "The ambiguous punctuation of this thinker's sentences, like \"Of this account which holds forever men prove uncomprehending,\" was decried by Aristotle in his Rhetoric. A fragment attributed to this thinker states that \"the way up and the way down are the same.\" In Lectures on the History of Philosophy, Hegel claimed that this thinker, not Socrates, should be considered the teacher of Plato. This teacher of Cratylus used the example of the harmony between the (*) bow and the lyre to illustrate their unity of opposites. In On Nature, this thinker, whom Diogenes Laertius called \"the weeping philosopher,\" claimed fire was the sole source of all substance and that the universe was in constant flux. For 10 points, name this Ancient Ionian philosopher, who Plato claimed believed that \"you can't step in the same river twice.\"", "answer": "Herakleitos [or Heraclitus]", "subcategory": "Philosophy", "category": "Philosophy"}, {"question": "Note to players: Description acceptable. In this conflict, one general could not declare war on the Suebi tribe because their leader, Ariovistus, was considered a \"king and friend of the people.\" This conflict started when the leader of a migrating Helvetian tribe died while fleeing from potential death by fire. The losing commander of this conflict was a king of the Arverni tribe. This conflict's namesake region was divided into (*) three equal parts, according to a set of commentaries. In this conflict's last battle, the Romans besieged a city by building a wall around their own army and another wall around Alesia. In that battle in this conflict, Vercingetorix was defeated by Julius Caesar. For 10 points, name this conflict where Rome conquered modern-day France.", "answer": "Gallic Wars [accept anything describing wars fought in Gaul by Julius Caesar]", "subcategory": "Ancient History", "category": "History"}, {"question": "The Book of Jubilees states that this character died in \"just retribution\" when his house collapsed on him. Dispute over the meaning of \"et-Yahweh\" has led some to claim this man was actually the son of God. A descendant of this man who works as a blacksmith is named for \"[this man's] spices\" and in one story causes Lamech to kill this man. Apocrypha names this man's sister Arwan as his wife, with whom he fathered (*) Enoch. God promises that anyone who harms this man will be punished seven-fold, and marks this man before exiling him to the land of Nod. This man's brother becomes a shepherd, while this man becomes a farmer. When God asks where that brother is, this man replies, \"Am I my brother's keeper?\" For 10 points, name this first son of Adam and Eve, who killed his brother Abel.", "answer": "Cain", "subcategory": "Religion", "category": "Religion"}, {"question": "Many of this author's first published poems cataloged his love affair with Friederike Brion in Sessenheim. R\u00fcdiger Safranski subtitled his biography of this author \"Life as a Work of Art.\" Johann Kestner inspired the character of Albert in one work by this author, who titled his autobiography \"Poetry and Truth.\" When working for Karl August, this author initially intended to write a work on William Tell, but he handed off the theme to his friend Friedrich Schiller. This author detailed his (*) southern travels in the \"Roman Elegies\" and the \"Italian Journey.\" This author wrote many of his best-known works while serving as a privy councilor in Weimar. For 10 points, name this author whose relationship with Charlotte Buff inspired his The Sorrows of Young Werther.", "answer": "Johann Wolfgang von Goethe", "subcategory": "Short Fiction", "category": "Literature"}, {"question": "The concept of this quantity was first introduced by Uhlenbeck and Goudsmit. This quantity is studied in a field that most often uses dilute magnetic semiconductors or Heusler alloys. A namesake type of \"-tronics\" studies this quantity's application in solid-state devices. The coupling of this quantity to motion contributes to fine structure. A 1921 experiment fired (*) silver atoms through a magnetic field to demonstrate the quantization of this quantity. Two electrons in the same orbital must have different values of this quantity. Electrons can have a value of plus or minus one-half for this quantity. For 10 points, name this quantity that represents the intrinsic angular momentum of a particle.", "answer": "spin [accept spintronics or spin-orbit coupling; prompt on angular momentum before mentioned]", "subcategory": "Physics", "category": "Science"}, {"question": "When a character in this play is asked about dactyls, he raises his middle finger in response. In this play, one character compares the sound of thunder to the sound his stomach makes after he drinks soup. A character in this play cites \"meteorological illiteracy\" in his refusal to pay a creditor, before asserting that interest is nonsensical since the amount of water in the world is constant. Near this play's end, one character insists on (*) beating his father since his father spanked him as a child. A character in this play dips the feet of a flea in wax to measure how far it can jump. This play includes a debate between Good Reason and Bad Reason. One character in this play is driven into debt by the horse-racing addiction of his son Pheidippides. For 10 points, name this play in which Xanthias and Strepsiades burn down Sophocles' Thinkery, by Aristophanes. --------------------------------------------------------------------------------", "answer": "The Clouds --------------------------------------------------------------------------------", "subcategory": "Drama", "category": "Literature"}], "bonuses": []}